[Music]
Reedman reads the Giver by Lois Lowry.
Narrated by Fraser Reed.
Chapter 23.
[Music]
Jonas felt more and more certain that the destination lay ahead of him,, very
near now, in the night that was approaching..
None of his senses confirmed it.. He saw nothing ahead except the endless ribbon
of road unfolding and twisting narrow curves.. He heard no sound ahead., Yet he
felt it:. felt that Elsewhere was not far away., But he had little hope left that
he would be able to reach it.. His hope diminished further when the sharp, cold
air began to blur and thicken with swirling white.. Gabriel,, wrapped in his
inadequate blanket,, was hunched,, shivering,, and silent in his little seat..
Jonas stopped the bike wearily,, lifted the child down,, and realized with
heartbreak how cold and weak Gabe had become..
Standing in the freezing mound that was thickening around his numb feet,, Jonas
opened his own tunic,, held Gabriel to his bare chest,, and tied the torn and
dirty blanket around them both.. Gabriel moved feebly against him and whimpered
briefly into the silence that surrounded them.. Dimly, from a nearby forgotten
perception as blurred as the substance itself,, Jonas recalled what the
whiteness was.. ""It's called snow,, Gabe,"," Jonas whispered. "Snow flakes. They fall
down from the sky,.
and they're very beautiful.". There was no response from the child who had once
been so curious and alert.. Jonas looked down through the dusk at the little head
against his chest.. Gabriel's curly hair was matted and filthy,, and there were
tear stains outlined in dirt on his pale cheeks.. His eyes were closed..
As Jonas watched,, a snowflake drifted down and was caught briefly for a
moment's sparkle in the tiny fluttering eyelashes..
Wearily he remounted the bicycle..
A steep hill loomed ahead.. In the best of conditions,, the hill would have been
a difficult,, demanding ride..
But now the rapidly deepening snow obscured the narrow road and made the
ride impossible.. His front wheel moved forward imperceptibly as he pushed on
the pedals with his numb,, exhausted legs., But the bicycle stopped.. It would
not move.. He got off and let it drop sideways into the snow.. For a moment, he
thought how easy it would be to drop beside it himself,, to let himself and
Gabriel slide into the softness of snow,, the darkness of night,, the warm comfort
of sleep.. But he had come this far.. He must try to go on.. The memories had
fallen behind him now,, escaping from his protection to return to the people of his community..
Were there any left at all?? Could he hold on to a last bit of warmth?? Did he
still have the strength to Give?? Could Gabriel still Receive?? He pressed his
hands into Gabriel's back and tried to remember sunshine.. For a moment, it
seemed that nothing came to him,, that his power was completely gone..
Then it flickered suddenly,, and he felt tiny tongues of heat begin to creep
across and into his frozen feet and legs.. He felt his face begin to glow and
the tense, cold skin of his arms and hands relax.. For a fleeting second, he
felt that he wanted to keep it for himself,, to let himself bathed in the
sunlight,, unburdened by anything or anyone else.. But the moment passed and
was followed by an urge,, a need,, a passionate yearning to share the warmth
with the one person left for him to love.. Aching from the effort,, he forced
the memory of warmth into the thin,, shivering body in his arms.. Gabriel
stirred.. For a moment, they were both bathed in warmth and renewed strength as
they stood hugging each other in the blinding snow..
Jonas began to walk up the hill..
The memory was agonizingly brief.. He had trudged no more than a few yards through
the night when it was gone and they were cold again.. But his mind was alert now.
Arming himself ever so briefly had shaken away the lethargy and resignation
and restored his will to survive.. He began to walk faster on feet that he
could no longer feel.. But the hill was treacherously steep;. he was impeded by
the snow and his own lack of strength..
He didn't make it very far before he stumbled and fell forward.. On his knees,,
unable to rise,, Jonas tried a second time..
His consciousness grasped at a wisp of another warm memory, and tried
desperately to hold it there,, to enlarge it,, and to pass it into Gabriel.. His
spirits and strength lifted with the momentary warmth, and he stood again.
Again,, Gabriel stirred against him as he began to climb.. But the memory faded,,
leaving him colder than before.. If only he had had time to receive more warmth
from The Giver before he escaped!.
Maybe there would have been more left for him now., But there was no purpose in ifies.
His entire concentration now had to be on moving his feet,, warming Gabriel and
himself,, and going forward.. He climbed,, stopped,, and warmed the both briefly
again, with a tiny scrap of memory that seemed certainly to be all he had left..
The top of the hill seemed so far away,, and he did not know what lay beyond..
But there was nothing left to do but continue..
He trudged upward.. As he approached the summit of the hill, at last,, something
began to happen..
He was not warmer;. if anything,, he felt more numb and more cold..
He was not less exhausted;. on the contrary,, his steps were leen and he
could barely move his freezing,, tired legs.. But he began, suddenly, to feel happy..
He began to recall happy times.. He remembered his parents and his sister..
He remembered his friends,, Asher and Fiona.. He remembered The Giver.. Memories
of joy flooded through him. suddenly., He reached the place where the hill
crested, and he could feel the ground under his snow-covered feet become level.
would not be uphill anymore.. ""We're almost there,, Gabriel,"," he whispered,,
feeling quite certain without knowing why..
""I remember this place,, Gabe."." And it was true..
But it was not a grasping of a thin and burdensome recollection;. this was
different.. This was something that he could keep.. It was a memory of his own..
He hugged Gabriel and rubbed him briskly,, warming him, to keep him alive..
The wind was bitterly cold.. The snow swirled,, blurring his vision. somewhere
ahead,, through the blinding storm,, he knew there was warmth and light..
Using his final strength, and a special knowledge that was deep inside him,,
Jonas found the sled that was waiting for them at the top of the hill.
Umly his hands fumbled for the rope.. He settled himself on the sled and hugged Gabe close..
The hill was steep, but the snow was powdery and soft,.
and he knew that this time there would be no ice,, no fall,, no pain.. Inside his
freezing body,, his heart surged with hope..
They started down.. Jonas felt himself losing consciousness and with his whole
being willed himself to stay upright at top the sled,, clutching Gabriel,, keeping him safe..
The runners sliced through the snow and the wind whipped at his face as they
sped in a straight line through an incision that seemed to lead to the
final destination,. the place that he had always felt was waiting, the Elsewhere
that held their future and their past..
He forced his eyes open as they went downward,, downward,, sliding,. and all at
once he could see lights,. and he recognized them now.. He knew they were
shining through the windows of rooms,.
that they were the red,, blue,, and yellow lights that twinkled from trees in
places where families created and kept memories,.
where they celebrated love. Downward,, downward,, faster, and faster..
Suddenly, he was aware with certainty and joy that below,, ahead,, they were
waiting for him;, and that they were waiting, too, for the baby.. For the first
time,, he heard something that he knew to be music..
He heard people singing. Behind him, across vast distances of space and time,.
from the place he had left,, he thought he heard music, too.. But perhaps it was
only an echo.
[Music]